<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AccessPlatform : Datastores</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Datastores">
            <p>
                The DataNucleus AccessPlatform is designed for flexibility to operate with any type of
                datastore. We already support a very wide range of datastores and this will only increase
                in the future. In this section you can find the specifics for particular supported datastores
                over and above what was already addressed for JDO and JPA persistence.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Relational
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="rdbms.html">RDBMS</a> : tried and tested since the 1970s, relational
                    databases form an integral component of many systems. They incorporate optimised querying
                    mechanisms, yet also can suffer from object-relational impedance mismatch in some
                    situations. They also require an extra level of configuration to map from objects
                    across to relational tables/columns.</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Documents
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="odf.html">Open Document Format (ODF)</a> : ODF is an international 
                    standard document format, and its spreadsheets provide a widely used form for publishing of
                    data, making it available to other groups.</li>
                    <li><a href="excel.html">Excel (XLS)</a> : Excel spreadsheets provide a widely used
                    format allowing publishing of data, making it available to other groups (XLS format).</li>
                    <li><a href="ooxml.html">Excel (OOXML)</a> : Excel spreadsheets provide a widely used
                    format allowing publishing of data, making it available to other groups (OOXML format).</li>
                    <li><a href="xml.html">XML</a> : XML defines a document format and, as such, is
                    a key data transfer medium.</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Map-Based
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="hbase.html">HBase</a> : HBase is a map-based datastore originated within Hadoop, following
                        the model of BigTable.</li>
                    <li><a href="appengine.html">Google AppEngine/Datastore</a> : 
                        <img src="../images/thirdparty.jpg" border="0" alt=""/>
                        Google AppEngine provides persistence to its own BigTable-based <i>Datastore</i> using a 
                        DataNucleus plugin, and its v3.0 release is designed to work with DataNucleus 3.2.
                        <b>Note that, at the time of writing, Google still hasn't released v3.0 of their plugin
                        and continues to release v1.0 as the default plugin; use that and everything is your problem</b>
                    </li>
                    <li><i><a href="https://github.com/pulasthi/Datanucleus-Cassandra-Plugin" target="_blank">Cassandra</a> : 
                        <img src="../images/thirdparty.jpg" border="0" alt=""/>
                        plugin providing persistence of all relation types to the Cassandra NoSQL datastore for JDO and JPA. 
						Works with DataNucleus 2.x</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Document-Based
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="mongodb.html" target="_blank">MongoDB</a> : 
                        plugin providing persistence to the MongoDB NoSQL datastore</li>
                    <li><i><a href="https://github.com/luigidellaquila/datanucleus-store-orientdb" target="_blank">OrientDB</a> : 
                        <img src="../images/thirdparty.jpg" border="0" alt=""/>
                        plugin providing persistence to the OrientDB datastore. Works with DataNucleus 2.x</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Graph-Based
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="neo4j.html">Neo4j</a> : plugin providing persistence to the Neo4j graph store</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Web-Based
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="json.html">JSON</a> : another format of document for exchange, in this
                    case with particular reference to web contexts.</li>
                    <li><a href="amazons3.html">Amazon S3</a> : Amazon Simple Storage Service.</li>
                    <li><a href="googlestorage.html">Google Storage</a> : Google Storage.</li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Object-Based
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="neodatis.html">NeoDatis</a> : an open source object datastore. This provides
                    fast persistence of large object graphs, without the necessity of any object-relational
                    mapping.</li>
                    <li><i>DB4O : an open source object datastore. DataNucleus (upto and including v3.0) provided a plugin
                        for db4o. This is now discontinued. Uses DataNucleus v3.0 if you wish to use this, or look in
                        our SVN for the plugin (no longer developed, so may not run against latest code)</i></li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Other
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="ldap.html">LDAP</a> : an internet standard datastore for indexed
                    data that is not changing significantly.</li>
                    <li><i><a href="http://www.vmforce.com/" target="_blank">VMForce</a> : 
                        <img src="../images/thirdparty.jpg" border="0" alt=""/>
                        plugin providing persistence to the Force.com datastore. Works with DataNucleus 2.x.
                        You can get the source code for this from 
                        <a href="https://github.com/forcedotcom/java-sdk/tree/master/jpa">here</a></i></li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/extensions/store_manager.html"><img src="../images/nucleus_plugin.gif" border="0" alt=""/></a>
                If you have a requirement for persistence to some other datastore, then it would likely be 
                easily provided by creation of a DataNucleus <i>StoreManager</i>. Please contact us via the
                forum so that you can provide this and contribute it back to the community.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>