<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>AccessPlatform : Datastores</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Datastores">
            <p>
                The DataNucleus AccessPlatform is designed for flexibility to operate with any type of
                datastore. We already support a very wide range of datastores and this will only increase
                in the future. In this section you can find the specifics for particular supported datastores
                over and above what was already addressed for JDO and JPA persistence.
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_rdbms.png" border="0" alt="RDBMS"/></td>
                    <td><a href="rdbms.html">RDBMS</a> : tried and tested since the 1970s, relational
                    databases form an integral component of many systems. They incorporate optimised querying
                    mechanisms, yet also can suffer from object-relational impedance mismatch in some
                    situations. They also require an extra level of configuration to map from objects
                    across to relational tables/columns.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_mapbased.png" alt="Map-Based" border="0"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="hbase.html">HBase</a> : HBase is a map-based datastore originated within Hadoop, following the model of BigTable.</li>
                    <li><a href="cassandra.html">Cassandra</a> : Cassandra is a distributed robust clustered datastore.</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_graphbased.png" alt="Graph-Based" border="0"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="neo4j.html" target="_blank">Neo4J</a> : plugin providing persistence to the Neo4j graph store</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_document.png" border="0" alt="Documents"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="odf.html">Open Document Format (ODF)</a> : ODF is an international standard document format, and its spreadsheets provide a widely used form for publishing of
                    data, making it available to other groups.</li>
                    <li><a href="excel.html">Excel (XLS)</a> : Excel spreadsheets provide a widely used format allowing publishing of data, making it available to other groups (XLS format).</li>
                    <li><a href="ooxml.html">Excel (OOXML)</a> : Excel spreadsheets provide a widely used format allowing publishing of data, making it available to other groups (OOXML format).</li>
                    <li><a href="xml.html">XML</a> : XML defines a document format and, as such, is a key data transfer medium.</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_webbased.png" alt="Web-Based" border="0"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="json.html">JSON</a> : another format of document for exchange, in this case with particular reference to web contexts.</li>
                    <li><a href="amazons3.html">Amazon S3</a> : Amazon Simple Storage Service.</li>
                    <li><a href="googlestorage.html">Google Storage</a> : Google Storage.</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_docbased.png" alt="Doc-Based" border="0"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="mongodb.html" target="_blank">MongoDB</a> : plugin providing persistence to the MongoDB NoSQL datastore</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><img src="../images/datastore/datastore_others.png" alt="Others" border="0"/></td>
                    <td>
                    <ul>
                    <li><a href="neodatis.html">NeoDatis</a> : an open source object datastore. This provides fast persistence of large object graphs, without the necessity of 
                    any object-relational mapping.</li>
                    <li><a href="ldap.html">LDAP</a> : an internet standard datastore for indexed data that is not changing significantly.</li>
                    </ul>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>

            <p>
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/documentation/extensions/store_manager.html"><img src="../images/nucleus_plugin.gif" border="0" alt=""/></a>
                If you have a requirement for persistence to some other datastore, then it would likely be 
                easily provided by creation of a DataNucleus <i>StoreManager</i>. Please contact us via the
                forum so that you can provide this and contribute it back to the community.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>