<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>DataNucleus : Services</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Services : Free and Commercial">
            <p>
                With any software, there are times when you need assistance to make full use of it. 
                Here at DataNucleus we want you to make the best of the software that we provide. 
                For that reason we provide both commercial and free support facilities.
            </p>
            <subsection name="DataNucleus : Commercial Support">
                <p>
                    Where you or your company require timely support when you need it without having to wait 
                    for somebody to respond on a forum we provide commercial support. You could, for example, 
                    have a preference for email support, or maybe phone support. If this is the case then we 
                    can discuss what would be possible. Please refer to 
                    <a href="http://www.datanucleus.com/services/index.html#support">our Support services</a> 
                    for details.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="DataNucleus : Free Support">
                <p>
                    DataNucleus provides its own <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org">online forums</a>
                    providing a place to discuss issues you are having. We don't guarantee to provide answers 
                    on this forum. It is simply a place where you could get some level of support when people 
                    have time. This may not be adequate for some people hence why we provide the commercial 
                    version above.
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Check the Documentation before anything else. The answer is usually there, 
                        either in a tutorial/example, or in one of the many guides.</li>
                    <li>Look in the <a href="logging.html">DataNucleus Log</a>. 
                        This usually contains a lot of information that may answer the issue. 
                        You can always configure the log to give more output.</li>
                    <li>Try a recent build to see if your version is out of date and the expected result is 
                        achieved with the latest nightly builds.</li>
                    <li>Go to the <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org" target="_blank">Online Forum</a> and 
                        ask. Always try to give as clear a description of the problem as possible, together 
                        with your input data, and any associated log output.
                        <b>Please be aware that we have very little time for this type of support and 
                        contributors to DataNucleus are more likely to get any available free support</b></li>
                </ol>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="DataNucleus : Commercial Consulting/Training">
                <p>
                    The DataNucleus experts are available for 
                    <a href="http://www.datanucleus.com/services/consulting.html">Consulting</a> for cases
                    where you need somebody intrinsically familiar with the DataNucleus system available
                    to resolve any particular implementation issues.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Similarly, if your company would like to build up your own experience in DataNucleus and
                    would like a kick start for this process the DataNucleus experts are available to provide
                    <a href="http://www.datanucleus.com/services/training.html">Training</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    One further possible use for DataNucleus consulting is to provide a plugin for a datastore
                    that we don't currently support. Do you have a datastore that you'd like to be able to persist
                    to using JDO or JPA ? We can help you achieve this. Contact us to discuss
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>