<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Eclipse Tutorial</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus JDO and Eclipse">
            <p>
                Eclipse provides a powerful development environment for Java systems. DataNucleus provides 
                its own plugin for use within Eclipse, giving access to many features of DataNucleus from the 
                convenience of your development environment.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="#install">Installation</a></li>
                <li><a href="#preferences_general">General Preferences</a></li>
                <li><a href="#preferences_enhancer">Preferences : Enhancer</a></li>
                <li><a href="#preferences_schematool">Preferences : SchemaTool</a></li>
                <li><a href="#enable">Enable DataNucleus Support</a></li>
                <li><a href="#metadata">Generate JDO MetaData</a></li>
                <li><a href="#persistence_xml">Generate persistence.xml</a></li>
                <li><a href="#enhancer">Run the Enhancer</a></li>
                <li><a href="#schematool">Run SchemaTool</a></li>
            </ul>

            <a name="install"/>
            <subsection name="Plugin Installation">
                <p>
                    The DataNucleus plugin requires Eclipse 3.1 or above. To obtain and install the 
                    DataNucleus Eclipse plugin select
                    <cite>Help -> Software Updates -> Find and Install</cite>
                    On the panel that pops up select
                    <cite>Search for new features to install</cite>
                    Select <cite>New Remote Site</cite>, and in that new window set the URL as
                    <b>http://www.datanucleus.org/downloads/eclipse-update/</b> and the name as DataNucleus. 
                    Now select the site it has added "DataNucleus", and click "Finish". 
                    This will then find the releases of the DataNucleus plugin.
                    <b>Select the latest version of the DataNucleus Eclipse plugin</b>. 
                    Eclipse then downloads and installs the plugin. Easy!
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <a name="preferences"/>
            <subsection name="Plugin configuration">
                <p>
                    The DataNucleus Eclipse plugin allows saving of preferences so that you get nice defaults
                    for all subsequent usage. You can set the preferences at two levels :-
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><b>Globally for the Plugin</b> : Go to <i>Window -> Preferences -> DataNucleus Eclipse Plugin</i>
                        and see the options below that</li>
                    <li><b>For a Project</b> : Go to <i>{your project} -> Properties -> DataNucleus Eclipse Plugin</i>
                        and select "Enable project-specific properties"</li>
                </ul>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="preferences_general"/>
            <subsection name="Plugin configuration - General">
                <p>
                    Firstly open the main plugin preferences page, set the API to be used, and configure the  libraries 
                    needed by DataNucleus. These are in addition to whatever you already have in your projects 
                    CLASSPATH, but to run the DataNucleus Enhancer/SchemaTool you will require the following
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>jdo-api.jar</li>
                    <li>datanucleus-core</li>
                    <li>datanucleus-api-jdo</li>
                    <li>datanucleus-rdbms : for running SchemaTool</li>
                    <li>Datastore driver jar (e.g JDBC) : for running SchemaTool</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Below this you can set the location of a configuration file for Log4j to use.
                    This is useful when you want to debug the Enhancer/SchemaTool operations.
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_prefs_general.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="preferences_enhancer"/>
            <subsection name="Plugin configuration - Enhancer">
                <p>
                	Open the "Enhancer" page. You have the following settings
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><b>Input file extensions</b> : the enhancer accepts input defining the classes to 
                        be enhanced. This is typically performed by passing in the JDO XML MetaData files. 
                        When you use annotations you need to pass in <i>class</i> files. So you select 
                        the suffices you need</li>
                    <li><b>Verbose</b> : selecting this means you get much more output from the enhancer</li>
                    <li><b>PersistenceUnit</b> : Name of the persistence unit if enhancing a persistence-unit</li>
                </ul>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_prefs_enhancer.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="preferences_schematool"/>
            <subsection name="Plugin configuration - SchemaTool">
                <p>
                	Open the "SchemaTool" page. You have the following settings
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><b>Input file extensions</b> : SchemaTool accepts input defining the classes to 
                        have their schema generated. This is typically performed by passing in the JDO 
                        XML MetaData files. When you use annotations you need to pass in <i>class</i> files. 
                        So you select the suffices you need</li>
                    <li><b>Verbose</b> : selecting this means you get much more output from SchemaTool</li>
                    <li><b>PersistenceUnit</b> : Name of the persistence unit if running SchemaTool on a persistence-unit</li>
                    <li><b>Datastore details</b> : You can either specify the location of a properties 
                        file defining the location of your datastore, or you supply the driver name, URL,
                        username and password.</li>
                </ul>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_prefs_schematool.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="enable"/>
            <subsection name="Enabling DataNucleus support">
                <p>
                    First thing to note is that the DataNucleus plugin is for Eclipse "Java project"s only.
                    After having configured the plugin you can now add DataNucleus support on your projects. 
                    Simply right-click on your project in <b>Package Explorer</b> and select 
                    <cite>DataNucleus->"Add DataNucleus Support"</cite> from the context menu. 
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_enable.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="metadata"/>
            <subsection name="Defining JDO XML Metadata">
                <p>
                    It is standard practice to define the MetaData for your persistable classes in the same 
                    package as these classes. You now define your MetaData, by right-click on a package in 
                    your project and select "Create JDO 2.0 Metadata File" from DataNucleus context menu. 
                    The dialog prompts for the file name to be used and creates a basic Metadata file for all 
                    classes in this package, which can now be adapted to your needs. You can also perform same 
                    steps as above on a *.java file, which will create the metadata for the selected file 
                    only. Please note that the wizard will overwrite existing files without further notice.
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_xml_metadata.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="persistence_xml"/>
            <subsection name="Defining 'persistence.xml'">
                <p>
                    You can also use the DataNucleus plugin to generate a "persistence.xml" file adding all
                    classes into a single <i>persistence-unit</i>. You do this by right-clicking on
                    your project, and selecting the option. The "persistence.xml" is generated under
                    META-INF for the source folder.
                    Please note that the wizard will overwrite existing files without further notice.
                </p>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="enhancer"/>
            <subsection name="Enhancing the classes">
                <p>
                    The DataNucleus Eclipse plugin allows you to easily byte-code enhance your classes using 
                    the DataNucleus enhancer. Right-click on your project and select "Enable Auto-Enhancement"
                    from the DataNucleus context menu. Now that you have the enhancer set up you can enable 
                    enhancement of your classes. The DataNucleus Eclipse plugin currently works by 
                    enabling/disabling automatic enhancement as a follow on process for the Eclipse build
                    step. This means that when you enable it, every time Eclipse builds your classes it will 
                    then enhance the classes defined by the available "jdo" MetaData files. Thereafter every 
                    time that you build your classes the JDO enabled ones will be enhanced. Easy! Messages 
                    from the enhancement process will be written to the Eclipse Console.
                    <b>Make sure that you have your Java files in a source folder, and that the binary class 
                        files are written elsewhere</b>
                    If everything is set-up right, you should see the output below.
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_enhancer.jpg" alt=""/>
                <br/>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="schematool"/>
            <subsection name="Generating your database schema">
                <p>
                    Once your classes have been enhanced you are in a position to create the database schema 
                    (assuming you will be using a new schema - omit this step if you already have your schema). 
                    Click on the project under "Package Explorer" and under "DataNucleus" there is an option 
                    "Run SchemaTool". This brings up a panel to define your database location (URL, login, 
                    password etc). You enter these details and the schema will be generated.
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/eclipse/jdo/eclipse_schematool.jpg" alt=""/>
                <p>
                    Messages from the SchemaTool process will be written to the Eclipse Console.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
